For the past few years,
خلال السنوات الماضية،
I've been spending my summers in the marine biological laboratory
اعتدت أن أمضي عطلة الصيف في المختبر البيولوجي البحري
in Woods Hole, Massachusetts.
في وودز هول، ماساتشوستس.
And there, what I've been doing is essentially renting a boat.
وهناك، جلّ ما فعلته هو استئجار قارب.
What I would like to do is ask you
وما أريده منكم هو
to come on a boat ride with me tonight.
أن تأتوا معي بجولة في القارب الليلة.
So, we ride off from Eel Pond into Vineyard Sound,
نبدأ من بحيرة (ثعبان البحر) باتجاه خليج (صوت الكرم)،
right off the coast of Martha's Vineyard,
تمامًا قبالة (ساحل مارثا)،
equipped with a drone to identify potential spots
وسترافقنا طائرة بدون طيار لتحديد المناطق التي من المحتمل
from which to peer into the Atlantic.
أن نراقب المحيط الأطلسي منها.
Earlier, I was going to say into the depths of the Atlantic,
سابقًا, كنت سأقول سنراقب أعماق المحيط الأطلسي،
but we don't have to go too deep to reach the unknown.
لكن ليس علينا التعمّق كثيرًا كي نصل إلى المجهول.
Here, barely two miles away
هنا، على بعد ميلين عن
from what is arguably the greatest marine biology lab in the world,
أعظم مختبر بيولوجي بحري في العالم،
we lower a simple plankton net into the water
نقوم بإنزال شبكة بسيطة لصيد العوالق في الماء
and bring up to the surface
ونحصل على أشياء
things that humanity rarely pays any attention to,
لا يعيرها الإنسان عادةً أيّ اهتمام،
and oftentimes has never seen before.
أو لم يرها في حياته أصلاً.
Here's one of the organisms that we caught in our net.
ها هي أحد الكائنات الحية التي التقطتها شبكتنا.
This is a jellyfish.
هذا قنديل بحر.
But look closely,
لكن دققوا النظر،
and living inside of this animal is another organism
يعيش داخل هذا القنديل كائن حي آخر
that is very likely entirely new to science.
هذا الكائن جديدٌ كلّيًا بالنسبة للعلماء.
A complete new species.
نوع جديد تمامًا.
Or how about this other transparent beauty
وماذا عن هذه الجميل الشفاف
with a beating heart,
ذو القلب النابض،
asexually growing on top of its head,
في قمة رأسه ينتج نسلاً بالطريق اللاجنسي،
progeny that will move on to reproduce sexually.
هذا النسل ينمو ويتكاثر بالطريق الجنسي.
Let me say that again:
دعوني أعيد صياغة ذلك:
this animal is growing asexually on top of its head,
هذا الكائن يتكاثر لاجنسيًّا في قمة رأسه ويعطي نسلاً،
progeny that is going to reproduce sexually in the next generation.
هذا النسل يتكاثر جنسيًّا في الجيل التالي.
A weird jellyfish?
قنديل عجيب؟
Not quite.
ليس تمامًا.
This is an ascidian.
إنه حيوان الأسيديان.
This is a group of animals
إنها مجموعة من الحيوانات
that now we know we share extensive genomic ancestry with,
نعلم الآن أننا نتشارك الأصول الوراثية معها بشكل كبير،
and it is perhaps the closest invertebrate species to our own.
وربما كانت النوع اللافقاري الأقرب لنا.
Meet your cousin,
قابلوا ابنة عمكم،
Thalia democratica.
(تاليا ديموكراتيكا).
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I'm pretty sure you didn't save a spot at your last family reunion
متأكد أنكم لم تحجزوا مكانًا في اجتماعاتكم العائلية
for Thalia,
من أجل (تاليا)،
but let me tell you,
لكن دعوني أخبركم،
these animals are profoundly related to us
هذه الحيوانات ذات صلة وثيقة بنا
in ways that we're just beginning to understand.
من نواحٍ عديدة بدأنا نفهمها مؤخّرًا.
So, next time you hear anybody derisively telling you
لذلك إذا أخبرك أحدٌ ما ساخرًا
that this type of research is a simple fishing expedition,
أنّ هذا النوع من الأبحاث هو مجرد رحلة للصيد،
I hope that you'll remember the trip that we just took.
أرجو أن تذكر الرحلة التي أخذتك بها للتو.
Today, many of the biological sciences only see value
اليوم، العديد من علماء البيولوجيا يرون الجدوى
in studying deeper what we already know --
في التعمق بدراسة الأشياء التي نعرفها مسبقًا
in mapping already-discovered continents.
في المناطق المُكتشفة مسبقًا.
But some of us are much more interested in the unknown.
لكن بعضنا مهتم أكثر بما هو مجهول حتى الآن.
We want to discover completely new continents,
نريد اكتشاف مناطق جديدة كُليًّا،
and gaze at magnificent vistas of ignorance.
و نتبحّر في روعة الأشياء المجهولة.
We crave the experience of being completely baffled
كنا بحاجة لأن نشعر بالحيرة التامة
by something we've never seen before.
أمام شيء جديد لم نره من قبل.
And yes, I agree
و نعم, أوافق بأنك
there's a lot of little ego satisfaction in being able to say,
ستشعر بالكثير من الرضى عن الذات عندما تقول،
"Hey, I was the first one to discover that."
"أنا أول مَن اكتشف ذلك."
But this is not a self-aggrandizing enterprise,
ولكن لا مكان هنا لمن يحبّون تضخيم ذاتهم،
because in this type of discovery research,
ففي هذا النوع من الأبحاث،
if you don't feel like a complete idiot most of the time,
إذا لم تشعر بأنك غبي بالكامل في أغلب الأوقات،
you're just not sciencing hard enough.
فمعناه أنك لا تبحث بما يكفي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So every summer I bring onto the deck of this little boat of ours
إذاً, في كل صيف، أحضر معي في قاربنا هذا
more and more things that we know very little about.
المزيد والمزيد من الأشياء التي لا نعرف عنها إلا القليل.
I would like tonight to tell you a story about life
أرغب الليلة أن أخبركم قصة عن الحياة
that rarely gets told in an environment like this.
التي نادرًا ما يتم الحديث عنها في بيئتنا.
From the vantage point of our 21st-century biological laboratories,
من وجهة نظر مختبراتنا البيولوجية الحاليّة في القرن 21،
we have begun to illuminate many mysteries of life with knowledge.
أننا بدأنا بكشف الكثير من الأمور الغامضة في الحياة.
We sense that after centuries of scientific research,
و نشعر أننا بَعد قرون من الأبحاث العلميّة،
we're beginning to make significant inroads
بدأنا نحرز تقدّمًا ملحوظًا
into understanding some of the most fundamental principles of life.
في فهم أحد أكثر مبادئ الحياة أهمية.
Our collective optimism is reflected by the growth of biotechnology
إن تفاؤلنا الجماعي ينعكس في تطور التكنولوجيا الحيوية
across the globe,
حول العالم،
striving to utilize scientific knowledge to cure human diseases.
هذا التطور يسعى لتوظيف المعرفة العلمية في علاج الأمراض.
Things like cancer, aging, degenerative diseases;
أشياء كالسرطان، التقدم بالسن، الأمراض التنكّسيّة،
these are but some of the undesirables we wish to tame.
نريد أن نتغلب على هذه الأمراض المستعصية.
I often wonder:
أتساءل أحيانًا:
Why is it that we are having so much trouble
لماذا نواجه العديد من الصعوبات
trying to solve the problem of cancer?
في إيجاد علاج للسرطان؟
Is it that we're trying to solve the problem of cancer,
هل لأننا نحاول ذلك،
and not trying to understand life?
بدون أن نحاول فهم الحياة أولاً؟
Life on this planet shares a common origin,
الحياة على هذا الكوكب تشترك بالأصل نفسه،
and I can summarize 3.5 billion years of the history of life on this planet
يمكنني اختصار 3.5 مليار سنة من حياة هذا الكوكب
in a single slide.
في صورة واحدة.
What you see here are representatives of all known species in our planet.
ما ترونه هنا يمثّل جميع الأجناس المعروفة في كوكبنا.
In this immensity of life and biodiversity,
أمام ضخامة الحياة والتنوع البيولوجي.
we occupy a rather unremarkable position.
نحن نشغل مكانًا لا يُذكر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Homo sapiens.
الإنسان البدائي.
The last of our kind.
الذي انحدرنا منه.
And though I don't really want to disparage at all
مع أنني لا أريد أبدًا أن أستخفّ
the accomplishments of our species,
بإنجازات جنسنا البشري،
as much as we wish it to be so and often pretend that it is,
ومهما كنا نتمنى أو ندّعي التطور،
we are not the measure of all things.
إلا أننا لسنا مقياسًا للجميع.
We are, however, the measurers of many things.
لكننا مقياس للكثير من الأشياء.
We relentlessly quantify, analyze and compare,
نحن نحدد ونحلل ونقارن بشكل صارم،
and some of this is absolutely invaluable and indeed necessary.
وذلك أحيانًا مهم جدًا وضروري.
But this emphasis today on forcing biological research to specialize
لكن اليوم هذا التشديد على إجبار الباحثين البيولوجيين على التخصص
and to produce practical outcomes
و تحقيق نتائج عملية
is actually restricting our ability to interrogate life
هو في الواقع يقيّد قدرتنا على الاستنباط من الحياة
to unacceptably narrow confines and unsatisfying depths.
بحدود ضيقة غير مقبولة و بعمق غير مرضٍ.
We are measuring an astonishingly narrow sliver of life,
نحن نتعامل مع جزء ضئيل جدًا من الحياة،
and hoping that those numbers will save all of our lives.
و نأمل أن ذلك الجزء سيساعدنا على إنقاذ حياة الجميع.
How narrow do you ask?
ما مقدار ضآلة ذلك؟
Well, let me give you a number.
حسنًا، سأعطيكم رقمًا.
The National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration recently estimated
الإدارة الوطنية للمحيطات والغلاف الجوّي قدّرت مؤخّرًا
that about 95 percent of our oceans remain unexplored.
أن حوالي 95% من محيطاتنا لم يتم استكشافها بعد.
Now let that sink in for a second.
الآن لنستوعب ذلك مجددًا.
95 percent of our oceans remain unexplored.
95% من محيطاتنا لم يتم استكشافها بعد.
I think it's very safe to say
أعتقد أنه يمكننا القول
that we don't even know how much about life we do not know.
أننا لا نعلم ما هو مقدار جهلنا فيما يتعلق بالحياة.
So, it's not surprising that every week in my field
لذا فمن غير المستغرب أنه أسبوعيّاً في اختصاصي
we begin to see the addition of more and more new species
نرى المزيد والمزيد من الأجناس الجديدة
to this amazing tree of life.
التي تنتمي لشجرة الحياة.
This one for example --
هذا الكائن مثلاً
discovered earlier this summer,
تم اكتشافه هذا الصيف،
new to science,
جديد بالنسبة للعلماء،
and now occupying its lonely branch in our family tree.
و الآن يشغل مكانه وحيدًا كجنس جديد في شجرة الحياة.
What is even more tragic
والمحزن أكثر
is that we know about a bunch of other species of animals out there,
أننا نعلم الكثير من الأجناس الحيوانية الأخرى،
but their biology remains sorely under-studied.
لكن من الناحية البيولوجية ما يزالون قيد الدراسة.
I'm sure some of you have heard about the fact
أنا متأكد أن بعضكم قد سمع عن
that a starfish can actually regenerate its arm after it's lost.
قدرة نجم البحر على إعادة تكوين أحد أذرعه إذا تم قطعه.
But some of you might not know
لكنكم قد لا تعرفون
that the arm itself can actually regenerate a complete starfish.
أن الذراع المقطوع نفسه يستطيع تكوين نجم بحر كامل.
And there are animals out there that do truly astounding things.
و هناك حيوانات يمكنها القيام بأشياء مذهلة أيضًا.
I'm almost willing to bet
أنا مستعدّ لأن أراهن أنّ
that many of you have never heard of the flatworm, Schmidtea mediterranea.
العديد منكم لم يسمع قَط بالدودة المسطّحة التي توجد في مناطق البحر المتوسط.
This little guy right here
هذه الدودة هنا
does things that essentially just blow my mind.
تقوم بأشياء تبهرني.
You can grab one of these animals and cut it into 18 different fragments,
يمكنك أخذ أحدها وتقطيعه إلى 18 جزءً،
and each and every one of those fragments will go on to regenerate
و كل جزء من تلك الأجزاء سيتطور ليشكّل
a complete animal
دودةً كاملة
in under two weeks.
في غضون أسبوعين.
18 heads, 18 bodies, 18 mysteries.
18 رأس، 18 جسم، 18 لغز.
For the past decade and a half or so,
منذ حوالي العقد والنصف تقريبًا،
I've been trying to figure out how these little dudes do what they do,
وأنا أحاول اكتشاف كيف تقوم تلك الحيوانات بذلك،
and how they pull this magic trick off.
كيف تفعل هذا الأمر السحري.
But like all good magicians,
ولكن كبقية السحرة المحترفين،
they're not really releasing their secrets readily to me.
لا يكشفون لي أسرارهم بسهولة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So here we are,
ها نحن ذا،
after 20 years of essentially studying these animals,
بعد 20 عامًا من التركيز على دراسة هذه الكائنات،
genome mapping, chin scratching,
ووضع الخريطة الوراثية، وحك الذقن،
and thousands of amputations and thousands of regenerations,
والآلاف من عمليات البتر وإعادة التكوين،
we still don't fully understand how these animals do what they do.
لازلنا لا نفهم بشكل كامل كيف تفعل الحيوانات ما تفعله.
Each planarian an ocean unto itself,
كل دودة بحد ذاتها،
full of unknowns.
مليئة بالأشياء الغامضة.
One of the common characteristics
أحد المميّزات المشتركة
of all of these animals I've been talking to you about
بين كل هذه الحيوانات التي ذكرتها لكم
is that they did not appear to have received the memo
هي أنهم لم يستلموا مذكّرة تقول
that they need to behave according to the rules
أن عليهم التصرف حسب القواعد
that we have derived from a handful of randomly selected animals
التي استمدّيناها من مجموعة عشوائية من الحيوانات الأخرى
that currently populate the vast majority
والتي تشكل حاليّاً الأغلبية الساحقة
of biomedical laboratories across the world.
من الحيوانات المدروسة في المخابر الطبية حول العالم.
Meet our Nobel Prize winners.
قابلوا الفائزين بجائزة نوبل.
Seven species, essentially,
7 أجناس بشكل أساسي،
that have produced for us the brunt of our understanding
هي التي منحتنا الجزء الأعظم من المعرفة
of biological behavior today.
حول سلوك الحيوانات اليوم.
This little guy right here --
هذا الصغير هنا --
three Nobel Prizes in 12 years.
فاز بثلاث جوائز نوبل خلال 12 عامًا.
And yet, after all the attention they have garnered,
ورغم أنهم يحظون باهتمام بالغ،
and all the knowledge they have generated,
ورغم كل هذه المعرفة التي قدّموها،
as well as the lion's share of the funding,
والتي كما يُقال حصة الأسد،
here we are standing [before] the same litany of intractable problems
ها نحن ذا نقف أمام نفس المعضلات
and many new challenges.
والكثير من التحديات الإضافية.
And that's because, unfortunately,
وهذا لسوء الحظ بسبب،
these seven animals essentially correspond
الأجناس السبعة من الحيوانات والتي تشكّل
to 0.0009 percent of all of the species that inhabit the planet.
0.0009 بالمئة من جميع الأجناس على كوكبنا.
So I'm beginning to suspect
لذلك بدأتُ أشكّ
that our specialization is beginning to impede our progress at best,
أن تخصصنا في أفضل أحواله بدأ يعيق تقدّمنا،
and at worst, is leading us astray.
وفي أسوأ الأحوال فإنّه يقودنا بالإتجاه الخاطئ.
That's because life on this planet and its history
وذلك بسبب أن الحياة وتاريخها على هذا الكوكب
is the history of rule breakers.
صنعها مَن خالفوا القواعد.
Life started on the face of this planet as single-cell organisms,
لقد بدأت الحياة على سطح هذا الكوكب كعضويّات وحيدة الخلية،
swimming for millions of years in the ocean,
تسبح لملايين السنين في المحيط،
until one of those creatures decided,
حتى قرر أحد هذه الكائنات،
"I'm going to do things differently today;
"سأقوم بشيء مختلف اليوم:
today I would like to invent something called multicellularity,
اليوم سأتطور إلى شيء يدعى الكائن عديد الخلايا،
and I'm going to do this."
سأطبّق ذلك".
And I'm sure it wasn't a popular decision at the time --
أنا واثق أنه ذلك القرار لم يحظَ بشعبيّة في ذلك الوقت
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
but somehow, it managed to do it.
لكن بطريقة ما، ذلك حدث فعلاً.
And then, multicellular organisms began to populate
بعد ذلك, الكائنات عديدة الخلايا بدأت تنتشر
all these ancestral oceans,
في جميع أرجاء المحيطات،
and they thrived.
و ازدهرت أيضًا.
And we have them here today.
كما نراها هنا الآن.
Land masses began to emerge from the surface of the oceans,
أجزاء من اليابسة بدأت تطفو إلى سطح المحيطات،
and another creature thought,
ففكرت مخلوقات أخرى،
"Hey, that looks like a really nice piece of real estate.
"تلك اليابسة تبدو جيدة للعيش عليها.
I'd like to move there."
نريد الانتقال إلى هناك".
"Are you crazy?
"هل جُننتم؟
You're going to desiccate out there. Nothing can live out of water."
ستصابون بالجفاف هناك، لا أحد يمكنه العيش خارج المياه".
But life found a way,
لكن الحياة تمكنت من ذلك،
and there are organisms now that live on land.
ويوجد الآن كائنات تعيش على اليابسة.
Once on land, they may have looked up into the sky
و كائنات اليابسة ربما نظرت مرّة إلى السماء
and said, "It would be nice to go to the clouds,
و قالت, "سيكون جميلاً لو صعدنا إلى الغيوم،
I'm going to fly."
سنقوم بالطيران إذاً".
"You can't break the law of gravity, there's no way you can fly."
"لن تستطيعوا التغلب على الجاذبيّة, يستحيل عليكم أن تطيروا".
And yet, nature has invented --
ومع ذلك، طوّرت الطبيعة
multiple and independent times --
خلال فترات زمنية مختلفة
ways to fly.
القدرة على الطيران.
I love to study these animals that break the rules,
أحبّ دراسة الكائنات التي تكسر القواعد،
because every time they break a rule, they invent something new
لأنهم في كل مرة يكسرون قاعدة ما، يطوّرون شيئًا جديدًا
that made it possible for us to be able to be here today.
جعلنا نصل إلى ما نحن عليه اليوم.
These animals did not get the memo.
تلك الكائنات لم تكترث للقواعد.
They break the rules.
وقامت بكسرها.
So if we're going to study animals that break the rules,
فإذا كنّا سندرس الحيوانات التي كسرت القواعد،
shouldn't how we study them also break the rules?
أليس علينا أثناء ذلك أن نكسر قواعدنا التي نتّبعها في الدراسة؟
I think we need to renew our spirit of exploration.
أعتقد أنّ علينا تجديد روح الأستكشاف لدينا.
Rather than bring nature into our laboratories
بدلاً من إحضار الطبيعة إلى مختبراتنا.
and interrogate it there,
و استجوابها هناك،
we need to bring our science
بل علينا أن نذهب بعلومنا
into the majestic laboratory that is nature,
إلى مختبر الطبيعة العظيم،
and there, with our modern technological armamentarium,
وهناك, بمساعدة تقنياتنا الحديثة،
interrogate every new form of life we find,
سنستجوب كلّ شكل جديد للحياة نجده،
and any new biological attribute that we may find.
وكلّ خاصّية حيويّة جديدة أيضًا.
We actually need to bring all of our intelligence
في الواقع نحن بحاجة أن نجلب كل ذكائنا
to becoming stupid again --
لكي نصبح جاهلين مرة أخرى
clueless [before] the immensity of the unknown.
كما كنا سابقًا.
Because after all,
لأنه في النهاية،
science is not really about knowledge.
العلوم لا تتعلق بالمعرفة.
Science is about ignorance.
العلوم تتعلق بالجهل.
That's what we do.
هذا ما نقوم به.
Once, Antoine de Saint-Exupéry wrote,
ذات مرة,،كتبَ (أنطوان دو سانت إكزوبيري)،
"If you want to build a ship,
"إذا أردت بناء سفينة،
don't drum up people to collect wood
لا تدعو الناس إلى جمع الخشب
and don't assign them tasks and work,
ولا تكلّفهم بالمهمات والأعمال،
but rather teach them to long for the endless immensity of the sea ..."
بل أخبرهم بالتفصيل عن مدى اتساع وروعة البحر".
As a scientist and a teacher,
كعالِم و معلّم،
I like to paraphrase this to read
أودّ أن أوضح أنّنا
that we scientists need to teach our students
نحن العلماء علينا تعليم طلابنا
to long for the endless immensity of the sea
عن مدى ضخامة البحر اللامتناهية
that is our ignorance.
هذا هو ما نجهله بالفعل.
We Homo sapiens are the only species we know of
نحن البشر نشكل الجنس الوحيد
that is driven to scientific inquiry.
الذي عليه البحث عن الحقائق العلميّة.
We, like all other species on this planet,
نحن, مثل كل الأجناس على هذا الكوكب،
are inextricably woven into the history of life on this planet.
على صلة وثيقة بتاريخ الحياة على هذا الكوكب.
And I think I'm a little wrong when I say that life is a mystery,
و أعتقد أنني مُخطئ قليلاً عندما أقول أن الحياة لغزٌ،
because I think that life is actually an open secret
لأنني بدأت أدرك أن الحياة هي سر مفتوح
that has been beckoning our species for millennia to understand it.
يومئ لنا منذ آلاف السنين لكي نفهمه.
So I ask you:
لذلك سأسألكم:
Aren't we the best chance that life has to know itself?
ألسنا نمثل الفرصة الأفضل للحياة كي تفهم نفسها؟
And if so,
و إذا كنّا كذلك،
what the heck are we waiting for?
فماذا ننتظر بحق الجحيم؟
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)